since the Libyan Revolution broke out, inspired by the waves of mass mobilization in both the Tunisian and the Egyptian revolutions. I joined forces with many other Libyans inside and outside Libya to call for a day of rage and to initiate a revolution against the tyrannical regime of Gaddafi. And there it was, a great revolution. Young Libyan women and men were at the forefront calling for the fall of the regime, raising slogans of freedom, dignity, social justice. They have shown an exemplary bravery in confronting the brutal dictatorship of Gaddafi. They have shown a great sense of solidarity from the far east to the far west to the south. Eventually, after a period of six months of brutal war and a toll rate of almost 50,000 dead, we managed to liberate our country and to topple the tyrant. (Applause) However, Gaddafi left behind a heavy burden, a legacy of tyranny, corruption and seeds of diversions. For four decades Gaddafi's tyrannical regime destroyed the infrastructure as well as the culture and the moral fabric of Libyan society. Aware of the devastation and the challenges, I was keen among many other women to rebuild the Libyan civil society, calling for an inclusive and just transition to democracy and national reconciliation. Almost 200 organizations were established in Benghazi during and immediately after the fall of Gaddafi -- almost 300 in Tripoli. After a period of 33 years in exile, I went back to Libya, and with unique enthusiasm, I started organizing workshops on capacity building, on human development of leadership skills. With an amazing group of women, I co-founded the Libyan Women's Platform for Peace, a movement of women, leaders, from different walks of life, to lobby for the sociopolitical empowerment of women and to lobby for our right
desde que estalló la revolución libia inspirada por las oleadas de movilizaciones masivas tanto de la revolución tunecina como de la egipcia. Uní fuerzas con muchos otros ciudadanos libios, dentro y fuera del país para llamar a un día de furia e iniciar una revolución contra el régimen tiránico de Gaddafi. Y lo logramos; fue una gran revolución. Mujeres y hombres jóvenes libios estaban en la vanguardia, exigiendo la caída del régimen, portando pancartas de libertad, dignidad y justicia social. Han mostrado una valentía ejemplar al enfrentar la brutal dictadura de Gaddafi. Han mostrado un gran sentido de solidaridad desde el Extremo Oriente, hasta el oeste, hasta el sur. Finalmente, después de un período de seis meses de guerra brutal y unas pérdidas de aproximadamente 50 mil muertos, logramos liberar nuestro país y derrocar al tirano. (Aplausos) Sin embargo, Gaddafi dejó una pesada carga, un legado de tiranía, corrupción y semillas de alteración. Durante cuatro décadas, el régimen tiránico de Gaddafi destruyó la infraestructura, la cultura y la estructura moral de la sociedad libia. Consciente de la devastación y de los desafíos, he querido, junto a muchas otras mujeres, reconstruir la sociedad civil libia, exigiendo una transición inclusiva y justa hacia la democracia y la reconciliación nacional. Se establecieron aproximadamente 200 organizaciones en Bengasi durante, e inmediatamente después de la caída de Gaddafi. Aproximadamente 300 en Tripoli. Después de un periodo de 33 años de exilio, volví a Libia y con un entusiasmo único, comencé a organizar talleres sobre el desarrollo de capacidades, y habilidades de liderazgo. Con un increíble grupo de mujeres fundamos la Plataforma de Mujeres Libias por la Paz, un movimiento de mujeres, líderes, de orientación muy diversa, para abogar por la autonomía sociopolítica de la mujer y por nuestro derecho
for equal participation in building democracy and peace. I met a very difficult environment in the pre-elections, an environment which was increasingly polarized, an environment which was shaped by the selfish politics of dominance and exclusion. I led an initiative by the Libyan Women's Platform for Peace to lobby for a more inclusive electoral law, a law that would give every citizen, no matter what your background, the right to vote and run, and most importantly to stipulate on political parties the alternation of male and female candidates vertically and horizontally in their lists, creating the zipper list. Eventually, our initiative was adopted and successful. Women won 17.5 percent of the National Congress in the first elections ever in 52 years. (Applause) However, bit by bit, the euphoria of the elections, and of the revolution as a whole, was fading out -- for every day we were waking up to the news of violence. One day we wake up to the news of the desecration of ancient mosques and Sufi tombs. On another day we wake up to the news of the murder of the American ambassador and the attack on the consulate. of the assassination of army officers. And every day, every day we wake up with the rule of the militias and their continuous violations of human rights of prisoners and their disrespect of the rule of law. Our society, shaped by a revolutionary mindset, became more polarized and has driven away from the ideals and the principles -- freedom, dignity, social justice -- that we first held. Intolerance, exclusion and revenge became the icons of the [aftermath] of the revolution. I am here today not at all to inspire you with our success story of the zipper list and the elections. I'm rather here today to confess that we as a nation took the wrong choice, made the wrong decision. We did not prioritize right. For elections did not bring peace and stability and security in Libya. Did the zipper list and the alternation between female and male candidates bring peace and national reconciliation? No, it didn't. What is it, then? Why does our society continue to be polarized and dominated with selfish politics of dominance and exclusion, by both men and women? Maybe what was missing was not the women only, but the feminine values of compassion, mercy and inclusion. Our society needs national dialogue and consensus-building more than it needed the elections, which only reinforced polarization and division. Our society needs the qualitative representation of the feminine more than it needs the numerical, quantitative representation of the feminine. We need to stop acting as agents of rage and calling for days of rage. We need to start acting as agents of compassion and mercy. We need to develop a feminine discourse that not only honors but also implements mercy instead of revenge, collaboration instead of competition, inclusion instead of exclusion. These are the ideals that a war-torn Libya needs desperately in order to achieve peace. For peace has an alchemy, and this alchemy is about the intertwining, the alternation between the feminine and masculine perspectives. That's the real zipper. And we need to establish that existentially before we do so sociopolitically. According to a Quranic verse "Salam" -- peace -- "is the word of the all-merciful God, raheem." In turn, the word "raheem," which is known in all Abrahamic traditions, has the same root in Arabic as the word "rahem" -- womb -- symbolizing the maternal feminine encompassing all humanity from which the male and the female, from which all tribes, all peoples, have emanated from. And so just as the womb entirely envelopes the embryo, which grows within it, the divine matrix of compassion nourishes the entire existence. Thus we are told that "My mercy encompasses all things." Thus we are told that "My mercy takes precedence over my anger." May we all be granted a grace of mercy. (Applause) Thank you.
de participación igualitaria en la construcción de la democracia y la paz. Me encontré con un entorno muy difícil en el periodo pre-electoral; un ambiente que estaba cada vez más polarizado, que se modeló de las políticas egoístas de dominación y exclusión. Lideré una iniciativa a través de la Plataforma de Mujeres Libias por la Paz, para abogar por una ley electoral más incluyente, una ley que le diera a cada ciudadano, sin importar su origen, el derecho de votar y presentarse en las elecciones, y lo más importante, estipular en los partidos políticos la alternación de los candidatos y candidatas vertical y horizontalmente en sus listas, creando la "lista cremallera". Con el tiempo, nuestra iniciativa fue aprobada y exitosa. Las mujeres ganaron un 17,5% del Congreso Nacional en las primeras elecciones en 52 años. (Aplausos) Sin embargo, poco a poco, la euforia de las elecciones y la revolución como un todo, fueron desapareciendo; todos los días encontrábamos noticias de violencia. Un día nos despertamos con la noticia de la profanación de mezquitas antiguas y tumbas sufíes. Otro día amaneció con la noticia del asesinato del embajador estadounidense y el ataque al consulado. Otro día nos despertamos con la noticia del asesinato de oficiales del ejército. Y cada día, cada día nos despertamos con el gobierno de las milicias y sus continuas violaciones de los derechos humanos de los presos y su falta de respeto de la ley. Nuestra sociedad, formada por una mentalidad revolucionaria, se polarizó más, y se ha alejado de los ideales y principios de libertad, dignidad, justicia social, que teníamos al principio. La intolerancia, la exclusión y la venganza se convirtieron en los íconos de las consecuencias de la revolución. No estoy aquí hoy en absoluto para inspirarlos con nuestra historia del éxito de la "lista cremallera" y las elecciones. Más bien estoy aquí hoy para confesar que nosotros, como nación, elegimos mal, tomamos la decisión equivocada, no priorizamos bien. Porque las elecciones no trajeron la paz, la estabilidad y la seguridad a Libia. ¿La lista cremallera y la alternación entre candidatos y candidatas trajeron paz y reconciliación nacional? No, no lo hicieron. ¿Qué pasó entonces? ¿Por qué nuestra sociedad sigue polarizada y dominada con políticas egoístas de dominación y exclusión, tanto por hombres como por mujeres? Tal vez lo que faltaba no eran solo las mujeres, sino los valores femeninos de compasión, misericordia e inclusión. Nuestra sociedad necesita el diálogo nacional y la creación de consenso más de lo que necesitaba las elecciones, que solo reforzaron la polarización y la división. Nuestra nación necesita la representación cualitativa de lo femenino más que necesitar la representación numérica y cuantitativa de ello. Necesitamos dejar de actuar como agentes de indignación y llamar a días de ira. Necesitamos comenzar a actuar como agentes de compasión y misericordia. Tenemos que desarrollar un discurso femenino, que no solo honre, sino también ponga en práctica la misericordia en lugar de la venganza, la colaboración en lugar de la competencia, la inclusión en lugar de la exclusión. Estos son los ideales que una Libia, destrozada por la guerra, necesita desesperadamente con el fin de alcanzar la paz. Porque la paz tiene una alquimia que trata de la interrelación y la alternación entre las perspectivas femeninas y las masculinas. Esa es la verdadera cremallera. Necesitamos establecer aquello de una manera existencial antes de hacerlo de forma sociopolítica. De acuerdo con un versículo del Corán "Salam"--la paz-- "es la palabra del Dios misericordioso, [rajeem, compasivo]". A la vez, la palabra "raheem", que se conoce en todas las tradiciones abrahámicas, tiene la misma raíz en árabe que la palabra "rahem"--útero--, simbolizando lo femenino y maternal, que abarca a toda la humanidad de la que hombres y mujeres, de la que todas las tribus y todos los pueblos han emanado. Y así, al igual que el útero cubre completamente el embrión, que crece dentro, la matriz divina de la compasión nutre toda la existencia. Así se nos dice: "Mi misericordia abarca todas las cosas". Así se nos dice: "Mi misericordia prevalece sobre mi ira". Que a todos se les conceda la gracia de la misericordia. (Aplausos) Gracias.